<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sundrie nevv and artificiall remedies against famine. Written by H.P. Esq. vppon thoccasion of this present dearth</title>
            <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849975</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849975</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09733)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 390:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sundrie nevv and artificiall remedies against famine. Written by H.P. Esq. vppon thoccasion of this present dearth</title>
                  <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by P[eter] S[hort] dwelling on Breadstreet hill, at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.P. = Sir Hugh Plat.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: New remedies against famine.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plants, Edible --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Food supply --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:1"/>
            <p>Sundrie new and Artificiall remedies againſt Famine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by H. P. Eſq; vppon thocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this preſent Dearth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="italic">Non eſt quo fugias à Deo irato niſi ad Deum placatum, <bibl>Aug.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of P. Short</figDesc>
               <head>P S</head>
               <q>ET VSQVE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed by P. S. dwelling on Breadſtreet hill, at <hi>the ſigne of the Starre.</hi> 1596.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:2"/>
            <head>NEW REMEDIES <hi>against famine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt, and principall, and moſt Chriſtian counſel that I can giue in theſe threatning daies of ſword and famine, is by harty praiers from a zealous heart to call vpon the name of the great and mighty <hi>Iehouah,</hi> and of the gratious and mercifull God of Iſraell, that it may pleaſe him to forget and forgiue our manifolde ſins and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which haue turned his fauorable countenance ſo long from vs, and brought downe from heauen ſo many clowdes of wrath vpon the fruites of the earth, as that the great hope of our harueſt is ſmitten and daunted already, and that it would pleaſe him of his fatherly goodnes by ſuch meanes as ſhall ſeeme beſt in his owne eyes, for the reliefe of theſe our preſent wantes, to turne this our penurie into plenty, and ſo to bleſſe vs with his bountifull hand, that we may all ſing a full ſong of thankeſgiuing vnto him, as wel for theſe new and vndeſerued fauours, as for that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victory of late obtained againſt our popiſh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, by the hand of thoſe honorable comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that haue already begun the peace of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:3"/>
            <p>Secondly, I could wiſh that all inferiour officers in their places, would haue a more charitable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious care in the execution of thoſe orders, which haue of late beene penned, and publiſhed with graue and deliberate aduiſe from the higher powers for the furniſhing of our markets with all kinde of graine. For the execution is the very life of the lawe, and the letter thereof though ſet downe by authority and graced with a moſt honorable <hi>Chorus,</hi> doeth giue ſome hope at the firſt, but no full ſatisfaction in the end vnleſſe the executing magiſtrate, together with thoſe high directors doe ioine hand in hand for the common good of their diſtreſſed countrie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I cannot want good will to wiſh though I haue no authority to command, that the very food of the earth euen the bleſsing of the Lord, ſhould be no longer ſubiect to this copyhold &amp; ſlauiſh tenure, of ſuch baſe &amp; vnmerciful lords, who vpon euery ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of foren ſcarcities, vpon euery petit tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea rumour of tranſportation onely, vpon faire weather, or foule weather, or any weather if they liſt, can make the ſame finable <hi>ad voluntatem Domini,</hi> and ſet what price they liſt vpon the buſhell. Is there no Court of Chauncery, neither in heauen nor vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, to bridle theſe couetous and vnmercifull Lords, yea and to ſtint them, that howſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe the God and giuer of all thinges to croſſe vs from the heauens, that yet no inferior perſon ſhould dare to exceede a certaine price to bee ſet downe by authority, vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcation of whatſoeuer graine hee ſhoulde ſo ouerrate vnto his poore and needye neighbour?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if euer Abſtinence were a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb facs="tcp:15156:3"/>an vertue, then nowe let it appeare amongſt vs, for why ſhould the rich men feaſt, when the poore are ready to famiſh? was there neuer but one <hi>Diues,</hi> and one <hi>Lazarus</hi> vpon the earth? or doe we want wit, or will, or grace to apply a parable? Here I may wel cry out and ſay to the rich, and fat weathers of our time, as <hi>Tully</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Anthony. Te miror An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoni, vt quorum facta imitêre, eoreum exitus non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſcere.</hi> I wonder at you ô you Epicures that you are not terrified with their deſtructions whoſe deeds you ſeeme to imitate. Well if wee haue brought our pampered bodies to thoſe delicacies, that wee can nowe aſwell leaue our liues, as our luſtes; yet if euerie rich man woulde ſpare but one meale in a weeke, and confer the eſtimate vppon the poore of the pariſh where hee dwelleth <hi>(nunquam nimis dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod nunquam ſatis diſcitur)</hi> I ſaie euen this one meale would ſerue wel to mend a whole weekes commons of a poore <hi>Subſciſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſift and laſt petition ſhould bee to moue vs to a Chriſtian charitie. And if that Romaine Poet and oratour, that ſententious <hi>Seneca</hi> in the danger and diſtreſſe of a priuate friende could giue in precept: <hi>Quòd amicorum neceſsitati magis occurrendum, quam ſuccurrendum,</hi> that we ought rather to preuent then relieue the neceſsity of a friend. Then what is to bee expected at our hands in a caſe of ſo great waight &amp; importance, as doth not only touch the credit of our profeſsion, but alſo the liues and welfare of many thouſands of our poore Chriſtian brethren, whereof ſome cannot labor, and many are without labor, and thoſe which labor can hardly maintaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by their labor. Yea if we would look more narrowly &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15156:4"/>pierce more deepely with a ſharpe eye into the threats and terrours of theſe times, though religion could work no charity in vs towards others, yet rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ciuill pollicy might preuaile ſo much with vs for our ſelues and thoſe which are deere vnto vs, that we ſhould not ſtay ſo long vntill our neighbours flames take holde of our owne houſes, nor trie the extremities that hunger, and famine may worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Thus much by way of Chriſtian aduiſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell, nowe becauſe I had rather be any way wanting then in good will vnto my natiue Countrey, vnto the which I confeſſe that I owe my wit, my wealth, my labour, my life, and whatſoeuer elſe I poſſeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my gracious ſoueraigne: and ſeeing that many graue, and learned ſermons haue already in vain bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vpon this Subiect, many careful prouiſions haue beene from time to time made and publiſhed from our prudent, and prouident Prince, and from thoſe honorable Senatours of our ſtate, which as yet can work no impreſſion in the ſteely, and adamant harts of our Engliſh Rookes and Cormorants, though I cannot win the goale in ſo great a purpoſe as I haue in hand, yet I wil bid the baſe to thoſe choiſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate wits of England, who if they would either aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate themſelues vnto me at the firſt, or ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me, when I haue begun this proud attempt, I would not doubt, but that by theſe our ioynt labours we ſhould fruſtrate the greateſt parte of theſe couetous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and by new, and artificial diſcoueries of ſtrange bread, drinke, and food, in matter and preparation ſo full of variety, to worke ſome alteration and change in this great and dangerous dearth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:4"/>
            <p>Neuertheles (though I do only break the yee, for thoſe that ſhal follow me in this kind) yet according to that poore talent of mine, I will trie mine owne ſtrength and confer as well my conceipt, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge herein: which though it bee neither ſuch as I could wiſh, nor as theſe vrgent times require, yet I wil be bold (in the fulnes of mine affection) to prefer and preſent the ſame to the view of the well diſpoſed Reader, whoſe courteous acceptation hereof, may one daie peraduenture wring from me ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of higher reach, and farther ſeruice then as yet I ſee either iuſt cauſe to promiſe or reaſon to ſpeake of.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in the treatiſe following my Author hath raunged ouer all manner of trees, plants, roots, greene pulſe and herbes, out of which hee might by any probabilitie draw any kind of ſuſtenance for the reliefe of man, I will onely content my ſelfe with the handling or preparation of ſome of theſe particulars which are moſt plentifull in their quantitie, leaſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue in their nature and moſt familiar with our ſoile and bodies, ſo as their offenſiue taſte beeing firſt remooued by arte, they may ſerue vs in a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manner and to our greater liking then nowe they do, either for bread, drinke or food.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Howe to take awaie a great part of that ranke and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauourie taſt of Beanes, Peaſe, Beechmaſt, Cheſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuttes, Acornes, Veches, and ſuch like.</head>
               <p>IF this may in ſome good meaſure bee performed, then I doubt not but that the bulke and body of our meale and flower will be much increaſed and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb facs="tcp:15156:5"/>at the leaſt for the poore mannes Table: then receiue mine owne experience therein. Boile your beanes, peaſe, beech maſt, &amp;c. in faire vvater, and if they be not yet pleaſing inough, change your vvater againe, and at the ſecond or third boyling, you ſhall finde a ſtrange alteration in taſte, for the water hath ſucked out &amp; imbibed the greateſt part of their rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then muſte you drie them (and if you thinke good, you may alſo hull them, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſet down hereafter in the Abſtract of <hi>Anchora Famis, &amp;c.</hi>) or elſe you may grinde them vnhulled, &amp; then make bread thereof, either ſimplie of it ſelfe, or with the addition of ſome third or fourth part of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wheat flower; or elſe for better expedition at the leaſt in drinke, if not in bread, you may take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground meale of them, and infuſe warme water thereon, and as it beginneth to coole, dreyne the ſame avvay, and reinfuſe freſh warme vvater till the taſte pleaſe you: then drie vp the meale, and make bread thereof ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimplie, or compounded as before. And as concerning the Cheſtnuts, we haue the experience of France therein already, vvhere in great abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they are ſpent and conſumed in their vſuall bread in diuers partes of that Country.</p>
               <p>The beech maſt doth yeeld a moſt ſweet and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate oile, and euery waie comparable with the nut it ſelfe, and therfore it is very probable that it wil make an excellent bread with a very ſmal correction: &amp; if there might be ſome eaſie vvaie or maner found out for the ready husking or hulling of them (which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no matter of any great difficulty) then I durſt promiſe a moſt rich &amp; plentiful oile of our own gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and ſeruiceable for many neceſſarie vſes. But
<pb facs="tcp:15156:5"/>if notwithſtanding my former preparation of beans, peaſe, &amp;c. the meale thereof do not yet content you, then worke it into paaſt, with a liquor firſt ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſome bruſed Annis ſeedes, licoras, or ſweet Fennell ſeedes, or with the ſeedes themſelues incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated in the paaſt, or for the auoiding of charge with pepperwort, Thime, winterſauery, penniroyal, &amp;c. For if you can but deceiue the taſte, you ſhall find the bread very harty, wholſome, &amp; nouriſhing. And whatſoeuer is here ſpoken of beanes, peaſe, &amp;c. may bee generally vnderſtoode of all other graine, ſeedes, plants, pulſe, rootes, &amp;c. And that which is ſeruiceable for bread, wil be much more tollerable in drinke: for the making wherof in ſome more cheap maner then as yet is known or vſuall amongſt vs you ſhal find ſome few notes of mine vpon the Abſtract following, in their ſeueral places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Certaine ſtrange and extraordinarie waies for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing of a priſoner, or other poore diſtreſſed crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when al hope of vſual victual is taken from him</head>
               <p>THeſe as I dare not warrant, ſo yet becauſe I haue receiued them either from good Authors, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the credible report of men of woorth, I will deliuer them as faithfully as I haue receiued them.</p>
               <p n="1">1 And firſt of al <hi>Paracelſus</hi> himſelfe affirmeth, that a freſh turfe or clod of earth, applyed euery daie vnto the ſtomach of a man, will preſerue him from fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing for ſome ſmal number of daies.</p>
               <p n="2">2 I haue heard many trauailers deliuer of their own knowledge and experience, that a man may liue 10. or 12. daies by ſucking of his owne bloud.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bapt. Port.</hi> telleth vs of a poor fellow vpon whom a ruinous houſe fel, and the man ſo hedged in vvith
<pb facs="tcp:15156:6"/>the floores and timber that fel vpon him, as that not being able to get out, he vvas forced to relieue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his owne vrine for 9. or ten daies, making his hand his cup to drinke in.</p>
               <p n="4">4 But the ſtrangeſt and moſt incredible of all the reſt, is that ſtory which Parſon <hi>Bateman,</hi> ſometime Parſon of <hi>Newington,</hi> had by relation of that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend father <hi>D. Grindal</hi> then <hi>Archbiſhop of Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> from the mouth of two Engliſh captiues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were impriſoned in Turky, and for their offence condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bee famiſhed to death, and eſcaped by this means. The keeper affecting his priſoners for thoſe good parts which he found in them, hauing receiued an oth of their ſecrecie, deliuereth vnto each of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſmal peece of Allom, which hee willed them fiue or ſix times a day to rowle vppe and downe in theyr mouthes. Howe at tenne daies ende, the great Turk ſending to knovv if the chriſtians were dead or aliue, and being informed of their liues, he commaunded that vppon paine of death no manne ſhould dare to relieue them with any maner of food. Now when 10 daies more were expired, and the like inquirie &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne made as before. Wel, qd. the Turk, if they can continew yet 10. daies more without food, I will ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the God of the chriſtians wil haue them preſerued, and they ſhalbe enlarged. The laſt 10. daies expiring, and the priſoners liues certified vnto the Turke, they were forthwith deliuered out of priſon, and returned for their ovvn countrey, and here diſcouered the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. The reaſon, and probabilitie hereof I vvill leaue for better<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Magitians</hi> then my ſelfe. For though vve might ſuppoſe that the ſalt of nature might receiue ſome ſtrength or vigour from this minerall ſalt, yet hovve the guts ſhould bee filled vvith ſo ſmall a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portion
<pb facs="tcp:15156:6"/>I cannot geſſe much leſſe determine.</p>
               <p n="5">¶ A ſift foode but receiuing ſome helpe from come vvas commended by <hi>Mendozza</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, wherewith he aſſured me vpon his honor that he had relieued a Spaniſhe towne, in an extreame dearth, and ſcarcity of victual, and therewithall ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed mee a loafe of that compoſition, which was of wheate ſtraw, chopt into ſhort peeces, and grounde with ſom proportion of wheat into meale. But ſince I haue beene farther informed, that the ſame prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe hath beene vſuall in harde yeares in ſome partes of England, and for mine owne better ſatisfaction, I cauſed ſome of the ſame flower to bee kneaded into bread, but it was verie browne in colour, and verie grettie in the mouth, and therefore it ſhoulde ſeeme that our ſtones be not ſo apt for the grinding of it, &amp; I haue heard ſome affirme, that the ſame cannot wel be ground but in a ſteele mill, or hand mil.</p>
               <p n="6">6 And the Eaſt Indians, as I haue read, do vſe to make little balles of the iuice of the hearbe Tabaco, and the aſhes of cockle ſhels wrought vp together, and dryed in the ſhadowe, and in their trauaile they place one of theſe balles betweene their neather lip, and their teeth, ſucking the ſame continually, and letting downe the moyſture, and it keepeth them both from hunger and thirſt for the ſpace of three or foure daies.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The ſeuenth and laſt of this kind, is that ſweet root called Licoras, which beeing chewed onely (if vve may beleeue <hi>Pliny</hi>) doth in ſmall quantitie ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie both thirſt and hunger, and yet maintaine ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtrength in the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to make an excellent bread of the rootes of Aaron called cuckowpit, or ſtarch rootes.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15156:7"/>
               <p>THe making thereof is ſet downe by a late writer in this manner. Firſt, the rootes that are large muſt be clenſed from all skin and filth, and then cut into ſmall and thin ſlices, the thinner you make them the ſooner they are prepared, ſeeth them in boyling vvater, ſo long as you finde the water hot and biting, and til the roots begin to waxe ſvveet. Then change your vvater, and poure freſh water vnto them, and ſo continue boyling vntill the vvater become ſweet, and that the roots haue loſt al their acrimony. Then take them out, and lay them abroad vpon Canuas, ſupported with frames, and being drie grinde them with hand mils, and they make a moſt white &amp; pure meale, which either of it ſelfe, or by the mixture of one thirde of wheate meale with it, maketh a moſt faire &amp; ſauory bread. This carieth ſome good ſence and likelihood of truth with it, for we finde by dailie experience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maketh as faire, if not a fairer ſtarch, then our vvheat. And therfore it were to be wiſhed, that ſome good husbandry were vſed in the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and multiplying of theſe rootes, obſeruing the nature of ſuch ſoile and place wherein they moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. And though it ſhould faile vs in this kind, yet we ſhall finde our labor richlie requited, if wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them into ſtarch only. But here it is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred, that the root muſt be gathered whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is plump full, and in his pride, which is about the latter end of March, and April al: for vvhen it beginneth once to ſpire, and that the ſap is run vp into the leaues, then the root ſhrinketh, &amp; alſo loſeth much of his vertue. Here a iuſt occaſion is offered to practiſe the like vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Turnep, whereof there are both good ſtore
<pb facs="tcp:15156:7"/>and the price of them likewiſe very reaſonable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Bread, and other food made of Pompions.</head>
               <p>THis fruit being both cheape, and great, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make a very ſauorie bread, if a little meale bee mixed therewith, yeelding food to a great number with a ſmal charge. And if you beſtowe ſugar, and other ſauce vppon it, it may alſo paſſe for a delicate diſhe. The maner of making the ſame is thus diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by <hi>Porta:</hi> Chooſe the greateſt and ripeſt Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, cut them into thinne ſlices, and take away the hard cruſt or coat, and the inner marrowe or ſoftnes, ſeeth them in boyling water, &amp; bring them to a pulp or pap, and then ſtreine it, adding therto a third part of meale or flower, and make it vp into bread, the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher you eate the ſame, the more pleaſant &amp; delicate you ſhal eſteeme it. But with mine Authors fauor: I thinke you wil find it in his beſt forme, and of fartheſt extention, when it is in his pap or pulpe, for his body is exceeding wateriſh, and vaniſheth away to a ſmall ſubſtance if you ſeeke to dry it. This I write by mine ovvne triall, yet peraduenture the Goord of Naples, which he calleth Cucurbita, may bee of a differing nature from our Pompions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to ſaue much flower, or meale that is loſt in all our vſual Corne mils, that grinde either with winde or water.</head>
               <p>IF I teach the Miller ſo to grinde his wheat, as that neither the ſtarchmaker (if I be not deceiued) ſhal haue ſtuffe to make his ſtarch with, except he grinde for himſelfe after the ancient maner; nor the brown Baker any bran to make horſebread withall, I hope
<pb facs="tcp:15156:8"/>that my fault will be pardonable at this time, becauſe I hold it much better to want flower about our necks then in our bellies, and that horſes ſhould ſtarue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their maiſters. The conceit is ſhort, and eaſie, and I hope without controlment. Let euerie Mill that grindeth corne, haue alſo a boulting mil annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto it, that the ſame mouer may play vpon both, and by ſhaking of the boulter make a diuiſion of the bran from the flower. This bran as ſoone as it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided from the flower muſt be returned againe into the hopper amongſt the reſt of the wheat that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground, and ſo as faſt as you gather any branne, you muſt mixe it with more corne: and by this meanes you ſhal haue much leſſe bran, and alſo more flower, thogh you would notwithſtanding this courſe, paſſe the ſame through a fine boulter againe. It is an vſual maner in the higher part of Germany to boult with theſe milles, but not to grinde ouer their bran againe in the firſt mill, for ought that I know, or as yet can learne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to make ſtarch without any corne.</head>
               <p>IT is wel knowne that thoſe <hi>Aaron</hi> rootes before mentioned, wil make a vvhite and delicate ſtarche. You muſt gather them in March or Aprill, waſhing them cleane, and paring avvay all the filthe, or foule skinnes from them, and after ſlicing them into thin ſlices, and ſo leauing them in faire cleere water, and changing your water euery 12. houres, for the ſpace of foure or fiue daies, till they become exceeding white and cleane; then ſtampe them, and force them through a ſtrainer with cleane water, and when the ſubſtance of the ſtarch is ſetled in the bottom, which
<pb facs="tcp:15156:8"/>will be in a few houres, then dreine away al the cleere water that fleeteth on the top, very gently, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the reſt being in flat earthen pans or cleane tubs to the Sun, which will attract or drawe vp all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and leaue a hard cake in the bottome. But in the winter time, when you cannot haue the Sunne of a ſufficient force for this purpoſe, then ſet your ſtone pannes, or pewter baſons wherein you haue ſtrained out your ſtarch vpon a pot with ſcalding water, and ſo you may drie the ſame in a ſufficient quantity for your own vſe all the yere long. And if you wold har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the ſame without charge, then place your pan vpon your biefe pot, &amp; ſo you ſhall make one fire to performe ſeuerall actions at once. But becauſe theſe rootes are not to be had in all places, nor at all times of the yeeare, therefore for a ſecond ſupplie I haue thought good to ſet downe this receit following.</p>
               <p>Take of the whiteſt <hi>Gumme Arabique</hi> that you can buy at the Grocers, let them beat the ſame into pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for you as big as hafell nuttes in their great mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, then take 3. ounces of this gumme, &amp; firſt waſh it in faire conduit water, in a ſtone baſon, ſtirring it vp and downe with your hands to take the filth from it; then waſh it againe with ſome more water, and powre that alſo away, and then to euery 3. ounces ſo waſhed put a wine pint of faire conduit water, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it vp and downe 3. or 4. times a daie to procure a ſpeedie ſolution or diſſoluing of the gumme: then couer your pan, and when all the gum is diſſolued, ſtreine the vvater through a cleane and thin linnen cloth, and reſerue the ſame in glaſſes well ſtopt, till you haue cauſe to vſe it. It will laſt ſweete at the leaſt three weekes after it is made. When you would vſe
<pb facs="tcp:15156:9"/>this ſtarch, if you deſire to haue your ruffes to carie a pure &amp; perfect white colour, you muſt mingle ſome blew with the water, ſtirring it vp and downe vvith your finger in a porrenger, and before the blewe ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the bottome, wet your ruffe therein, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie wring it out againe; then pat it till it be cleare, and after ſet it, as you doe in your common ſtarch, I doe finde by experience, that halfe the time that is loſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other maner of ſtarching, is here gained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by reaſon that your ſtarch is in a thinne vvater, the Lawne &amp; Cambricke wil be ſoone cleared, and with much leſſe beating. And I think that a ſecond profit will here likewiſe fall out by the way, viz. that your Lawne and Cambricke wil laſt much longer: for (if I be not deceiued) the continuall patting, or beating thereof betweene the hands in our vſuall ſtarching, worketh a great fretting and wearing of the ſame. And I doubt not, but that there be many other ſortes of graine, pulſe and rootes, which wil make as good ſtarch as vvheate, which at this time I leaue vnto the ſtudious indeuours of thoſe that are carefull for the common good. It may bee that at my better leiſure I may handle this ſubiect more at large, but now the preſent times inforce me, to deliuer that knovvledge which I haue. And thus much for ſtarch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Sweete and delicate cakes made without ſpice, or Sugar.</head>
               <p>SLice great and ſweete parſnep rootes (ſuch as are not ſeeded) into thin ſlices, and hauing waſhed &amp; ſcraped them cleane, dry them, and beat them into powder (here a mil would make a greater diſpatch)
<pb facs="tcp:15156:9"/>ſearcing the ſame through a fine ſearce, then knead two partes of fine flower with one part of this pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and make the ſame into cakes, and you ſhal find them to taſt very daintily. I haue eaten of theſe cakes diuers times in mine owne houſe <hi>Quaere,</hi> what may be done in carots, turneps, and ſuch like rootes after this maner.</p>
               <p>Here I thinke it not impertinent to the purpoſe, which I haue in hand, to wiſh a better ſuruey to bee made of my booke of Husbandry, being a parcell of the Iewel houſe of Art and Nature, printed an. 1594. Wherin ſundry new ſorts of Marle are familiarlie ſet down, and publiſhed for the good of our Engliſh far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: amongſt the which, thoſe waſte aſhes of the Sopeboilers (for ſuch as dwel neer vnto the Citie of London, or may by eaſy water cariage conuey them vnto their hungry and leane grounds) haue a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal place for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inriching of al cold, moiſt &amp; weeping grounds. The book is to be had at the Greyhound in Paules churchyard. And if there were ſuch plenty as I could wiſh of thoſe ſhauings or cuttings of horne, wherof thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work for lanthorns only make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt ſtore, I would the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect of the infinit exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend that before any other manuring of ground whatſoeuer, &amp; for the only garden doung y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I know, although for arable ground I muſt needes confes, that I haue one ſecret, not as yet made kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen or common to the world, that wold proue more general, &amp; more eaſie of price then any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer that I as yet haue either heard, or read of, but for ſom reaſons beſt knowne vnto my ſelfe, I doe as yet forbeare the diſcouery therof.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a certaine victuall in the forme of hollovv pipes, or wafers, wherewith, as alſo with a
<pb facs="tcp:15156:10"/>defenſatiue oile for his armours, peeces, and other weapons, I furniſhed ſir <hi>Frances Drake</hi> in his laſte voyage, which hath beene well approued and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by ſundry of his folowers vpon their return for England, whereby I was the more encouraged to make a ſecond triall thereof in the Beare vvhich vvent latelie for <hi>CHINA.</hi> This foode I am bold to commende in this place, both bicauſe it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth <hi>ad propoſitum,</hi> and for that I knowe that if the maiſters, owners, or Mariners of ſhips, vvould adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedlie looke into it, they ſhoulde finde it one of the moſte neceſſarie, and cheape prouiſions that they could poſſibly make, or carie with them. The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commendation whereof, reſteth vppon theſe few branches following:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 ¶ Firſt, it is very durable, for I haue kept the ſame both ſweet and ſound, by the ſpace of 3. yeares, and it agreeth beſt with heat, which is the principal deſtroyer of Sea victuall.</item>
                  <item>2 It is exceeding light: for which qualitie Sir <hi>Frances Drake</hi> did highly eſteeme thereof, one man may carie vpon any occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of land ſeruice, ſo much thereof, as vvill be ſufficient to relieue two hundred men a day.</item>
                  <item>3 It is ſpeedily dreſſed, for in one halfe houre, it is ſufficientlie ſodden, by which property it may alſo ſaue much fevvell and fiering, which occupieth no ſmall roome in a ſhip.</item>
                  <item>4 It is freſh, and thereby very pleaſing vnto the Mariner in the midſt of his ſalt meats.</item>
                  <item>5 It is cheape, for in this dearth of corne, I dare vndertake to feed one man ſufficientlie, for 2. pence a meale.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15156:10"/>
                  <item>6 It ſerueth both in ſteede of bread and meate, whereby it perfourmeth a double ſeruice.</item>
                  <item>7 Not being ſpent it may be laide vp in ſtore for a ſecond voyage.</item>
                  <item>8 It may be made as delicate as you pleaſe, by the addition of oyle, butter, ſugar, and ſuch like.</item>
                  <item>9 There is ſufficient matter to bee hadde al the yeare long, for the compoſition thereof.</item>
                  <item>10 And if I might once finde any good incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement therein, I vvould not doubt but to deliuer the ſame prepared in ſuch ſort, as that without anye farther dreſſing thereof, it ſhould bee both pleaſing, and of good nouriſhment vnto a hungry ſtomach.</item>
               </list>
               <p>¶ Al thoſe which are willing to victual their ſhips therewith, if they repaire vnto me, I wil vpon reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable warning, furniſh them therewith to their good contentment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A ſpeedie or preſent drinke which Trauailers may make for themſelues <hi>(extempore)</hi> when they are diſtreſſed for want of good beer or ale at their Inne.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of faire water, put thereto fiue or ſix ſpoonfuls of good Aqua compoſita, which is ſtrong of the Annis ſeedes, and one ounce of Sugar, and a branch of Roſemary, brew them a prety while out of one pot into another, and then is your drinke prepared. Or if you leaue out ſugar, it wil bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing enough. I haue beene crediblie informed that diuers Gentlemen of good credit, when they trauail abroad, and cannot like the taſte or reliſhe of theyr drinke, that they vſe no other then the aforſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and find the ſame both to refreſh and coole
<pb facs="tcp:15156:11"/>them very well, neither are they troubled with the rawneſſe of cold water, by reaſon that it hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſome correction by the Aqua compoſita, &amp; that the Annis ſeedes doe giue a delicate taſte vnto it. It were not amiſſe for all Seaman to cary ſome ſtore of Aquauitae with them, that when their wine, Cider, Perry, and beer are ſpent, they may tranſmute theyr water into the ſaide drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A cheape liquor for poore men, when malt is extreme deere.</head>
               <p>IF a poore man in the time of flovvring, doe gather the toppes of Heath with the flowers, which is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called and knowne by the name of Linge in the Northerlie partes of this Realme, and is that plant whereof our common heath bruſhes are made, and laie vppe ſufficient ſtore thereof for his own prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being well dried and carefully kept from putrefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or molding, he may at all times make a very plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing and cheape drinke for himſelfe, by boiling the ſame in faire water, with ſuch proportion thereof, as may beſt content his owne taſte. And this liquor is commended vnto mee, by one of the moſt ſufficient profeſſours of Phyſicke of our times, and that vpon his ovvne and often experience, for a moſt vvhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and medicinable drinke, as vvell for the Liuer as the Spleene. It may be graced with a little licoras in the decoction, if he ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p>¶ I haue alſo heard Sir Frances Drake affirme, that faire water and vinegar mixed in a due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth make a fine cooling and refreſhing drinke
<pb facs="tcp:15156:11"/>in hot wether, which he eſteemed for a rare ſecret at the Sea. And I haue alſo knowne them that haue made a voluntary drinke thereof on the lande, when they haue hadde ſufficient choice of others before them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to brew good and wholſome Beere, without any Hoppes at al.</head>
               <p>SInce my profeſſion in this booke, is in ſome ſorte to anatomize both Art and Nature, without anie regard of priuate mens profits, whom it either may eſſentiallie or accidentallie touch, I am bolde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without crauing any leaue to doe good: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, or rather to confirme and ratifie an ancient opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; practiſe, which long ſince in the great dearth and ſcarſitie of hops, many brewers of this land haue beene inforced to put in vſe for the better ſuporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their weake and declining eſtates. But bicauſe they failed in proportion (without the which there can be nothing compleat or abſolute) they ſuffered a good conceit to die in the birth. And no maruell then, if wormwood notwithſtanding it bee a ſimple ſo highly commended of all the ancient and nevve Herbariſts, for his great and ſingular effects in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, be in a maner vtterly abandoned of al the bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in our time (except a fewe that can make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betvveene fiue ſhillinges, or 5. pound charge, when hops are ſolde for 50. <hi>s.</hi> an hundred) ſeeing as yet not any one of them hath ſo clerkly wrought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſimple, as to couer and hide the taſt therof, from the wel mouthed ale-cunners of our commonwelth, which weaknes of theirs, bicauſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth wholy in
<pb facs="tcp:15156:12"/>the want of a due proportion between the mault and other beere corne, in reſpect of vvormwood, I haue thought good to ſet downe a ſufficient direction for thoſe that are wiſe, and willing to doe good both to themſelues, and to their countrey, wherby they may eaſilie euen in one daies practiſe attaine to the full perfection therof. Suppoſing then that your worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood is either cut down in the leafe before it be ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or being ſeeded that it is cut into ſhort peeces, whereby there may be made an equal mixture of the whole bulke together (for you muſte note that the ſeedie tops are much ſtronger and much more oylie then the reſt of the leaues or ſtalkes) make firſt a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of 4. ounces of hoppes with nine gallons of water (which is the proportion which ſome Bruers in ſome ſorts of drinke doe vſe) and when you haue gotten out by ebulition or boyling, the full ſtrength and vertue of them, keepe the ſame, and begin like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with ſome ſmall proportion of wormewoode to the like quantitie of vvater as before; and vvhen you haue beſtowed as much time and fire therein, as you did about the hops, then taſte each of them by it ſelfe, and if you finde the ſame to exceede the firſt in bitterneſſe, then beginne with a leſſe proportion of Wormewood, and ſo reiterate your worke, till you haue equally matched the one with the other: then may you ſafely proceed by the rule of proportion to a barrell, and from thence to a tun, and ſo to a whole bruing. Neither let the bitterneſſe of Wormwood in his preſent taſte any thing diſmay you, for if you did but taſte the decoction of hoppes onelie before the mixture of ground malt (which doth wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweeten the ſame) you would thinke it a very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt
<pb facs="tcp:15156:12"/>licour to be wrought vp into ſo pleaſing a drinke as our ordinary beere doth ſhew it ſelfe to bee: for it is the hop onely which maketh the eſſential differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene beere and ale, and that by alaying the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding luſciouſnes of malt by his bitternes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both vniting themſelues togither, become a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourie and wholſome drinke for mans bodie: which may be in euery reſpect as well performed in worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, as in the hop, yea, &amp; peraduenture with Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taury, artichoke leaues, or <hi>Aloes hipatique,</hi> as ſome work maiſters haue confidentlie affirmed vnto mee. And though the hop bee vſuallie in drinke, and the wormewood onely in medicine, wherby ſome may happilie be perſwaded, that it is inconuenient for men that are in health to drinke a medicine continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>allie to their meate: yet let this be a ſufficient anſwer to that obiection, that it is the doſe only that maketh the difference heerein. For I can aſſure you in mine owne experience, and by the experience of one of the beſt experienced Bruers in London, who yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that if you giue a double or treble quantitie of Engliſh hoppes to an ordinarie guile of ſtrong beere, you ſhall finde the ſame to bee a ſufficient preparatiue to your body for the beſt purgation that ſhall be miniſtred after. And this is the reaſon whie Venice Turpentine, which being miniſtred in a ſmal doſe, is giuen for the ſtrengthening of the back, and to ſtay the running of the reynes: yet if it be taken in the quantitie of an ounce at once, it will purge ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlie in diuers bodies. So then either let there be no more taſte of wormewood, then there is of hops in our drinke, and we ſhall finde no difference in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but ſuch as ſhall commend and grace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood
<pb facs="tcp:15156:13"/>beyond the hoppe; or let beere bee aduanced with the hop to the bitternes of wormwood wine, &amp; ſo we ſhal find the hop far to exceed the wormwood in his maligne qualitie.</p>
               <p>Thus much I haue thought good to publiſhe, for the credit of wormwood and for the benefit of this Iland in ſundry reſpectes, which I ſhall not neede to particularize at this time, becauſe they are ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie knovvne to all men. And though I knowe I may be ouerweyed either with the Flaunders Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, or with the great hop maiſters of Englande, whoſe foundation is ſo deeply laide, that a fewe looſe lines can neither ſhake nor ſtir the ſame: yet eyther knowing or at the leaſt perſwading my ſelfe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the truth, before I giue it ouer, I will craue the libertie of the ſchooles, <hi>quòd fiat controuerſia.</hi> And in the meane time, thoſe which will not bee ſatisfied of the wholſom and rare medicinable helps of the one, togither with the weake and feeble vertues of the other (which was but a hedgebird the other daye, thogh now it be perking ſo proudlie vpon his poles) I wil refer them to the learned Herbals of <hi>Dioſcorides Matheolus, Doctor Turner, Dodoneus, Turnizerus,</hi> and the reſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:13"/>
            <head>An abstract of certaine frugall notes, or obſeruations in a time of Dearth or famine, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning bread, drink, and meate, with ſome other circumſtances belonging to the ſame, taken out of a Latin writer, intituling his booke, <hi>Anchora fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis &amp; ſitis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, for the auoiding of all putrefaction, aſwell in bread, as in corne, it is very requiſite that they bee perfectly dried, or gentlie parched, either in the ſun, or by the warmth of the ayre, or elſe in the want of theſe two, in ſome apt ouen, <hi>or rather in a Stoue,</hi> but with ſuch care, as they doe not burne, or ſauour of aduſtion.</p>
            <p n="2">2 After the baking of your bread, it is neceſſarie that the ſame be left in the ouen, wel cloſed, for ſome reaſonable time, the heate thereof being leſſened by degrees, for ſo the bread being thoroughly baked, &amp; ſuffered to coole of it ſelfe again, will ſatisfie the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a man in double proportion to that which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Each kind or ſort of bread being a little toſted ouer the coales, and afterwards ſopped in wine, will fil or glut exceedingly: ſuch a breakefaſt as this taken in the morning, is a ſufficient repaſt for the vvhole daie after.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The meale of parched corne doth fill the gutte exceedinglie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Bread may bee made of Rice, Indian millet, or Turkiſh wheat, either by decocting the whole grain in water, and ſo bringing it to the forme of a pulteis, and after baking the ſame, or elſe by grinding it into meale, but the latter way maketh the fairer bread.
<pb facs="tcp:15156:14"/>
               <hi>This may as ſufficientlie bee performed with our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie wheat, for ought that I can imagine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 All maner of pulſe, as Lentils, vetches, beanes, &amp; ſuch like, if they be firſt rubbed ouer in Lee, &amp; then hulled and after ground, they will yeelde both fayrer meale, and better bread.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Paaſt, or dowe is ſoone baked vpon thin plates of iron or braſſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Thoſe which ride poſte, are oftentimes content both to bake their bread, and alſo to roſt their meate vnder the ſeates of their ſaddles, <hi>here I think that our climate will proue too cold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 Men muſt be broughr by degrees, and not too ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlie from their vſual and natural food and drinke, into theſe artificiall diets.</p>
            <p n="10">10 A pulteis or hochpot, made of flower or meale ſodden amongſt apples, peares, plums, and ſuch like fruite, or of ſome bread and water, or the broath of fleſhe that hath beene toſted in the ſmoke, or vvith milke wel boiled togither, doth fil the ſtomack more then thrice ſo much of dry bread eaten alone, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, if the ſame be high boiled to a ſtifnes, or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtencie.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Such like compoſitions do alſo extend farther in the ſatisfieng of hungry mawes, being made of Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, or dry, hard, or ſtale grated bread. And by this meanes one loafe wil go as far as two new loaues.</p>
            <p n="12">12 All ſortes of good cakebread, or ſpicebread ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a conuenient time in faire vvater, will conuert the vvater into a moſt pleaſant or wholſome drinke, the bread notwithſtanding being very wholſome to be eaten.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Pound your pepper, ginger, and ſuch like ſpices,
<pb facs="tcp:15156:14"/>and hauing ſteeped them in water, place the ſame well couered ouer a gentle fire, and then worke your paaſt with the imbibition, or decoction therof. And by this meanes your ſpice will extend much farther in cakebread. And the ſame ſpice alſo being nevve pounded or beaten, may bee afterward wrought vp in paaſt for cakebread. Here you may practiſe vpon theſe plants, which be hot and wholſome withall: as the wilde Creſſes, otherwiſe called Pepperwort, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingale, Thime, Orrace, Iſop, Winterſauery, Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royall, and ſuch like hearbes inſtead of ſpices.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Some of theſe artificiall kinds of bread &amp; drinke, if there be any left that may be wel ſpared, will ſerue for the feeding and fatning of cattel, geeſe, Hennes, Hogs, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="15">15 The ſmell or ſent of bread <hi>(I thinke hee meaneth that, which is new and hot from the Ouen)</hi> doth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the body, and refreſh the ſpirits greatly. <hi>Some commend the ſpirites of bread extracted by diſtillation, as a moſt ſoueraign preſeruatiue in the conſumption, and other pining diſeaſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 If any of theſe artificial foods or drinkes doe hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen to offend, either in colour, taſt, <hi>or ſauor,</hi> they may be helped with hony, ſugar, ſaffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wine, annis ſeeds, Coriander ſeedes, <hi>ſweet Fenel, Cinamon,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="17">17 In the time of neceſſity, euen greene corne taken as it groweth of it ſelfe, or a little parched or dryed againſt the fire, or ſteeped, or boiled in wine, <hi>or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> affoordeth a reaſonable kind of ſuſtenance.</p>
            <p n="18">18 The diſtilled water of oats, doth ſo warme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, as it doth ouercome the ſenſes. <hi>It is wel known that many do brue a verie ſtrong &amp; mightie drink with
<pb facs="tcp:15156:15"/>malted oates, howe profitable the ſame might bee to all our Engliſh Brewers (if there might bee ſufficient ſtore of them had) in a dearth of wheat and barlie, the ſame being rightlie matched, or rather maſtered a little with the hop, to alter their taſt: they can beſt tell that haue made their priuate experience and profit of them, when others very inconſideratly haue runne on in their common, and chargeable courſe of brewing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 The licour of the Birch tree is both whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſauerie, and deſerueth to be recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his kind.</p>
            <p n="20">20 There may bee an excellent extraction made of ale, which you may terme either a ſpirit, or a quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence, and that in a ſmal doſe, far more excellent then all the tartareous, ſulphureous, or mercuriall preparations. <hi>If the Authour do heere meane any philoſophicall courſe, it will bee both too curious and coſtly for the common ſort of people: if onely a well recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> Aquauitae, <hi>or an euaporation of the phlegmaticke parte to a thicke body, I cannot ſee how we ſhal raiſe any ſtore, or quantity of matter to furniſh the ſubiect which we haue in hand If he meane phyſically, we will reſerue the ſtrict examination thereof, till a fitter occaſion bee offered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 The meale of ſuch corne as is ground in the month of Auguſt, is remembred amongeſt the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of beſt credit, to keepe and laſt beſt all the yeare after.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Such bread as is made vp of the flower of dry beanes is moſt ſtrong in nouriſhment, and may bee corrected of his taſte by the addition of Comin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed. And it is alſo a vſuall matter in Germanie to make drinke of Beanes. <hi>Our Engliſh Brewers doe alſo
<pb facs="tcp:15156:15"/>find good vſe of them amongſt other corne in a ſmal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, wherin they haue a ſpecial care not to ſurcharge the reſt of their beere corne, with too great a quantitie of Beanes, leaſt they ſhould giue a bad ſmacke or farewell to their beere: but I am verely perſwaded that if either beanes, or peaſe were artificially handled according to the maner before expreſſed, that they would not onelie proue ſeruiceable, and that in a large maner for Beere only, but alſo for the making of wholſome, ſweet, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 Of Veches firſt hulled, and of the hearbe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phace, which receiueth diuers tranſlations, and is called Dandelion, Prieſtes crowne, Swines ſnowt, Monks head, Dogs teeth, or common Cicory, may be made a bread ſo as it be mixed with a conuenient proportion of other vſual meale, for it yeeldeth a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie faire and ſauerie flower, as the Authour teſtifieth of his owne experience the ſame may bee corrected with Annis ſeede, Fenell ſeede, Coryander ſeede, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Both bread, and drinke may alſo bee made of Lentils.</p>
            <p n="25">25 Breade may bee made of Pannicke, as alſo of Millet, whoſe ſeede euen in a ſmall quantity doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe greatly both in bulcke, and ſubſtance.</p>
            <p n="26">26 A ſolid, and wholſome bread may be made of wheat ſtarch. <hi>But ſuch bread, by reaſon of his price, will haue no fit place heere except euery priuate man do make his own prouiſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27 A decoction of Annis ſeede, Fennell ſeede, Caraway ſeede, and ſuch like, either in wine, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is a moſt wholeſome drinke. <hi>Hereunto may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a decoction alſo of Licoras with Annis ſeedes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:15156:16"/>in faire water in a dew proportion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">28 Of Beechmaſt, Acorns, and the barkes or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of trees that are wholſome, a conuenient drinke may be had.</p>
            <p n="29">29 Muſhroms will ſpring aboundantly if you ſlit the barkes of the blacke, and white Poplar, and burie them in furrowes wel dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged. So likewiſe the white Poplar being cut off cloſe by the ground, and wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with warme water well ſeaſoned with leauen, in foure daies ſpace will bring forth moſt pleaſant, and delicate Muſhroms. <hi>Theſe being dreſſed in their kinds are accompted amongſt the moſt luſty, &amp; ſtirring meats with the Italians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30 A good bread may be made of the Rape, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uew, being firſt ſcorched, and after ſodden, and then baked.</p>
            <p n="31">31 A breade may bee made of the powdred, or ground leaues of the peare tree, apple tree, beech &amp; oake, and ſo likewiſe of drinke.</p>
            <p n="32">32 Dow may be kneaded vp with wine, vineger, or ale, if you would make the ſame hot, and harty. <hi>But I thinke the new muſt of wine, or the beſt wurt of ale, or beere much better, for that we may wel doubt, or rather aſſure our ſelues that the whole ſpirit of wine, or ale wil flie away in the baking, becauſe the ſame had firſt wrought it ſelfe into a bodie, whereas in wurt that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came to workemanſhip, the fire or ſpirit doth as yet lie cloſe, and couched within it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33 A dronken breade may bee made with ſpirit of wine and flower. <hi>But I thinke that common</hi> Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſita <hi>would proue ouerchargeable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34 A paaſt conſiſting of meale, and the oyle of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues,
<pb facs="tcp:15156:16"/>or other fruit, or ſeeds mixed together may be made into bread.</p>
            <p n="35">35 Mizaldus reporteth of a certaine Trauailer, who vndertaking a long iourney did relieue himſefe with one pound of the oile of Violets, and ſoft greaſe mix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed togither, and therewith he preſerued himſelfe by the ſpace of ten daies. The like effect hath alſo beene found in the oile of Almonds mixed with the greaſe of a Cow, and that by reaſon of the clammines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="36">36 A bread made of Egges is both wholeſome, and more filling then other ordinary bread, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the ſame bee kneaded vp with the yeiſt of the ſtrongeſt beere or ale.</p>
            <p n="37">37 Thoſe egs are moſt carefully to be gathered, and kept, which are laid from the new moone in Auguſt, others do rather commend the waine, and the time of both the Sunſteads. And newe laid egs will keepe long in dry chaffe, or bran.</p>
            <p n="38">38 An excellent bread may be made with milke ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leauened, or vnleauened, and of exceeding nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment being taken but in a ſmal quantity, but they fill more if reſty bacon being fried bee alſo incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated therewith.</p>
            <p n="39">39 A man may liue with milke only, and it wil ſerue inſteed of meat, and drinke, and medicine.</p>
            <p n="40">40 A glutting kind of bread may bee made of newe cheeſe, and likewiſe of olde being grated; mixed, and wrought vp with meale. For it commeth all to one ende whether we eate breade and cheeſe ſeuerally, or both mixed together.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:17"/>
            <head>A petition to the curteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eère I haue thought good (Gentle Reader) to intreat thus much fauor at thy hands, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing my new fire of Coleballes, togither with ſome other fewe inuentions, firſt mentioned in mine Apology, do as yet attend ſome courtly fauours, wherby they cannot ſo preſently as I wiſh, breake foorth into the publike ſeruice of this land: that thou wouldeſt for a little time (which I hope is now drawing to his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod) intertain them with a good conceipt and kind opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, not regarding the cenſures of thoſe ignorant, or malicious ſpirits of our age, who preſuming to know the ſimples of my fire, may happily range into baſe and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue matter, and thereby labor to diſcredite that ſecret, whoſe compoſition they could neuer yet reach vnto, nor, if they had the particulars, were they able to combine &amp; knit them with their left handed workmanſhip.</p>
            <p>And for the better ſatisfaction of my welwiſhing friends, &amp; the full confutation of mine vndeſerued foes, I would haue them to vnderſtand, that ſeeing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſecrets, haue not onlie bin ſeen, and allowed, but at this preſent are alſo countenanced by thoſe which are right Honorable in their places: that from hencefoorth they will ſcorne the malice both of viperous tongues, as alſo of ſlanderous pens, if any man ſhould happen to bee ſo extreamlie, or deſperatelie mad, as to take vpon him to argue vpon that proiect, whereof he can neither finde a <hi>medium,</hi> nor <hi>communes terminos,</hi> and therfore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posſible to conclude <hi>Sillogiſticè ſinon in Bocardo</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15156:17"/>
            <p>ANd if I ſhal heere diſcouer a ſecret both newe and profitable for our Engliſh Maltſters, whereof as yet there is not ſo much as any model extant, and that I could fal into M. <hi>Aiax</hi> veine, and had ſome of his glib paper, &amp; gliding pens, I might ſoon ſcribble ten ſheets, and ſell euerie ſheet for two pence, towarde neceſſarie charges: and in the end conclude the expectation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie leaues, in a few ſweeter lines then he hath done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me: but becauſe I wil bind my ſelfe to no ſuch priuy preſidents, I will deliuer my conceipt in as plain and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tearmes as I may.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>New Malt kils for wood or Seacole.</head>
               <p>INſtead of thoſe ſpars which ſupport the hearcloth place a few ſingle quarters, ſawed in equall partes, here and there ſcatteringly, or make what other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you ſhall thinke beſt, to beare a floore or plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme of lead, which (for the auoiding of charge) may be made of ſheet lead thinlie driuen: and if you meane to vſe Seacole, then muſt you haue a grate of yron bars to lay your coles on, and let there be foure vents within a foot of the floore, made in equall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance each from other, both to draw vp the heate and ſteame of the fire, as alſo to conuey the ſmoake by ſmal leaden pipes into ſome woodden trunke or tunnel of brick or plaiſter: and if you find the lead too hot for the barley, you may either leſſen your fire till you haue attained a true degree thereof, or elſe you may ſpread a hearecloth vpon the lead, and ſo auoid the danger of haſtie malting, peraduenture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteame of boiling water, iſſuing out of a great copper veſſell
<pb facs="tcp:15156:18"/>being placed ouer the fire, may giue a ſufficient heat for this purpoſe. And heere I hope, that both the bad ſent and taſt which is vſuallie found in wood dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-malt, as alſo the continuall attendance vppon a ſtraw fire will be much auoided: beſides that ſauing which wil fall out in ſuch ſhires, as affoord either wood or Seacole in any plentifull manner. I haue beene alſo crediblie informed, that a fire of beane ſtalkes, maintained in an vſual kill, will defraye his owne charge, by reaſon of the aſhes, which are more worthe then the fewell it ſelfe. But whether they ſerue beſt for the making of glaſſe, ſope, or ſalte Peter, I cannot determine, onely I know them to be full of a ſtrong and ſharpe ſalt, and ſuch as ſerueth the Surgeon to make his <hi>Cawſticke</hi> withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A new and extraordinary meanes for the inriching of arable grounds.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe the multiplying of corn is not great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abhorring from our purpoſe, and ſeeing the greateſt part of Dearth, muſt of neceſſitie begin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarſitie of graine, I will here (without praying in aide of M. <hi>AIAX,</hi> or of his ſtale marginal notes, whoſe reformation hath already more offended the eares of Honorable perſons, then his firſt ſalts could euer offende their noſes) make a publike offer to all thoſe Gentlemen and Farmers of England, whoe dwell in ſuch partes of this Realme, as doe neither yeeld any ſtore of Marle, or other common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie dung or ſoile, how they ſhall bee ſufficientlie furniſhed, with a newe and plentifull <hi>Compoſt,</hi> and whereof there haue beene already ſundrie
<pb facs="tcp:15156:18"/>and rich trials made, whoſe quantitie ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede eight buſhels, whoſe yearelie charge ſhal not amount to xviii. pence the acre <hi>communibus Annis,</hi> one year with another, and whoſe nature is ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted and diſguiſed, as that one neighbor, yea M. <hi>Aiax</hi> himſelfe, though he were preſent at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing or ſcattering thereof, ſhall not be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne what his next neighbour hath doone to his ground. In which ſecret, all thoſe whome the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſhal finde willing and worthie of the ſame, may vppon reaſonable compoſition, become owners of the skill, aſwell for their owne as for the good of their countrey. Neither doe I know any iuſt obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, why the ſame ſhould not inrich aſwell paſture ground as arable.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
